

## **CFMS 2018-19 President-elect Nominee**

Name: Christina Schweitzer School: University of Calgary

Year of Study: 3/3



## **Bio/Letter of Intent** (250 words max):

Dear friends and colleagues,

It has been a privilege serving you, the CFMS members, as your VP Communications for the last seven months. Every day, I have the pleasure of sharing the work that you do in your medical schools, communities, and through the CFMS with our members, partners, and the general public. I love sharing the successes and achievements of Canada's medical students, and advocating for the issues that are important to you. It would be an honour to continue to do so as your CFMS President. Through my experience as VP Communications, I have been involved in all of the CFMS' portfolios and am familiar with the activities, challenges, and future directions of the organization. I have a strategic plan for how we can best leverage our partnerships and public profile to achieve the advocacy goals that you, our members, have identified as priorities.

A key issue for the CFMS is Unmatched Canadian Medical Students. I have been heavily involved in developing our public relations strategy and coordinating with media, including ten publications in April alone.

As President, I would propose to the Federal Minister of Health the creation of a national coordinating body for managing residency numbers and distribution, ask that unmatched CMGs be discussed at the Federal-Provincial Health Ministers

Round Table, and explore having centralized national CaRMS interviews in one location. I look forward to chatting with you more about the ideas I have for the role and to answering your questions!

# Christina Schweitzer

MPhil (Cantab), BSc Medical Student and Gates Cambridge Scholar VP Communications, Canadian Federation of Medical Students (CFMS)

867 Lanky Court, Yellowknife, NT, X1A 2G4

vpcommunications@cfms.org

+15872258165

#### **Education**

### Medical Doctor (MD) Student and Nat Christie Scholar

2016-2019

University of Calgary, Cumming School of Medicine, Calgary AB, Canada

• Clinical clerk in Yellowknife, Northwest Territories

### MPhil in Biological Science (Immunology) and Gates Cambridge Scholar University of Cambridge and the MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Cambridge, UK

2013-2015

• Laboratory research degree, with thesis on antibody-directed intracellular immunity to viruses

## BSc in Engineering and Chancellor's Scholar, First Class Honours

2009-2013

Queen's University, Kingston ON, Canada

• Chemical Engineering major, Biochemical/Biomedical Engineering specialization

## **BSc in Engineering (International Exchange)**

2011-2012

École Supérieure de Chimie Physique Électronique de Lyon (CPE Lyon), Lyon, France

• Full-year academic exchange, with French as the language of instruction (fluent in French)

### **Professional Experience**

#### Healthcare Analyst, Sociable Data, London, UK

2015-2016

Performed research, analysis and consulting at a pharmaceutical competitive intelligence firm

Teaching Assistant & Project Manager, Queen's University, Kingston, Canada

2012-2013

### **Selected Leadership and Teamwork Experience**

Medical School (University of Calgary):

#### **VP Communications, Canadian Federation of Medical Students (CFMS)**

2017-2018

 Leading internal & external communications of the CFMS, the national body representing over 8,000 medical students at 15 medical schools across Canada

#### Editor-in-Chief, The Calgary Guide to Understanding Disease

2017-2018

 Overseeing writing, editing, publication and development of free, open access online medical learning resource www.thecalgaryguide.com. Have authored 5 topics and reviewed & edited 26

### Advocate, Federal & Provincial Medical Student Political Action Days

2016-2018

- Met with MPs in Ottawa to discuss response to the opioid crisis and indigenous mental wellness
- Met with MLAs in Edmonton to discuss mental health policy and cannabis tax revenue investment

#### **TEDMED Research Scholar**

2018

• Editorial evaluation of TEDMED speakers under consideration for TEDMED's 2018 conference

Graduate (University of Cambridge):

#### Secretary and Vice President, Darwin College Students' Association

2014-2015

Represented over 600 graduate students; responsible for internal affairs, operations and elections

#### Varsity Athlete (Half Blue), Cambridge University Women's Ice Hockey Blues 2014-2015

Competed in the 2015 Varsity Match against Oxford University and at National Championships

### First Boat Rower, Darwin College Boat Club

2013-2015

• Awarded Blades in Lent Bumps 2015, competed in four sets of Bumps with Darwin W1 boat

### Head of Marketing and Communications, Cambridge University Science and Policy Exchange (CUSPE)

2014

- Managed the public profile of CUSPE (website, newsletters, Facebook, Twitter), 2000 members
- Organized the first Annual Policy Review debate at the Royal Society in London

#### **Operations Officer, Darwin College May Ball**

2014

Organized logistics of hospitality for over 800 people, managing a budget of ~\$33,000 & 40 staff

Undergraduate (Queen's University):

## Deputy Leader of the Opposition, Queen's Model Parliament,

2010, 2011, 2013

- **House of Commons of Canada** (Ottawa)
- Developed diplomatic and public speaking abilities (French and English) in the House of Commons
- Author of a bill on foreign policy, senior leadership role in a caucus of 83 MPs in 2013

#### **Board of Directors, Engineering Society**

2012-2013

- Oversaw corporate initiatives (café, pub, newspaper, apparel, science camp, orientation week)
- Reviewed finances, budgets and annual reports (annual budget of \$1.2 million, 2,400 members)

#### Chair, Strategic Planning Committee, Engineering Society

2012-2013

Led strategic, long-term planning for the 8 corporate initiatives operated by the Society

#### Co-President (Internal Affairs), Friends of MSF: Queen's

2010-2011

• Raised awareness for MSF (Médecins Sans Frontières / Doctors Without Borders) initiatives

#### **Selected Awards**

Joule '17 in 2017: 17 physicians who helped shape the future of healthcare in 2017' 2017

University of Calgary Nat Christie Medical Entrance Award, \$17,000

2016-2019

Gates Cambridge Scholarship, ~\$200,000

2013-2015

• Top international scholarship at the University of Cambridge, from Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation

Queen's University Jean Royce Graduate Fellowship, \$21,000

2013-2014

#### Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC)

Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship (declined), \$17,500

2013-2014

Queen's University Chancellor's Scholarship, \$36,000

2009-2013

#### Selected Published Peer Reviewed Commentaries

Schweitzer C et al. (2018) Youth and the opioid crisis: Strategies for intervention and the British Columbian experience. University of British Columbia Medical Journal 9(2)(34-35).

Schweitzer C. (2017). The Time is Right for a National Pharmacare Program for Canada. University of Toronto Medical Journal 94(3).

Schweitzer C. (2014). A Good Death. The Gates Scholar. (On legalization of assisted suicide).